<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Wattwerks</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/chatter.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2013-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Lead acid batteries</title><link href="/lead-acid-batteries.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:,2013-06-23:lead-acid-batteries.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;BATTERY ABUSE&lt;br /&gt;
A battery is not an investment or an asset. It's a consumable - each discharge leads it closer to it's ultimate death. Battery maintenance is not simply about topping it up with distilled water every now and then but also about understanding your consumption and your sources of energy to minimize cycling your batteries.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damaging batteries by over-charging is also a common occurrence. MPPT solar charge controllers are focussed on maximizing the power output from the solar array. This is generally an optimal strategy for grid tied current inverters where the current has somewhere to go - either to the load or the grid. But in off-grid systems if there's not enough load, the batteries get charged at a raised voltage. This is desired if the batteries aren't fully charged but once they are, there is risk of overcharging as at higher voltages water gets electrolyzed into hydrogen and oxygen which escape. The electrolysis and escape of gases causes spillage of the electrolyte if the battery isn't a sealed type. Cell reactions for a lead acid battery are &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lead-acid_battery"&gt;well known&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember - an ignored battery will end up in a land-fill polluting groundwater sooner than a well maintained one. If you've ever wondered why your kids aren't as clever as you then look no further at the lead and other toxins in our water supply retarding their brain development.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="battery"></category></entry><entry><title>Too hot for PV</title><link href="/too-hot-for-pv.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:,2013-05-19:too-hot-for-pv.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There has been a huge rush over the last few years to build PV plants in Gujarat &amp;amp; Rajasthan based on the solar irradiation received. Little attention is paid to how modules perform at 40 deg C in dusty conditions. Contrary to expectations, plant operators may find better performance in the winter.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met an experienced installer who said that he measured a 150Wp poly-crystalline panel (manufacturer will remain un-named) putting out 3A @ 19V at mid-day in 40 deg heat.  Most module manufacturers will list the loss in power per degree above 25 deg C in their data sheets but what most won't tell you is that the loss isn't linear - the hotter it gets the greater the losses are. So the data sheet will state 0.5% power loss per deg C - so a 7.5% loss if you're at 40 deg. But this 0.5% is per deg above 25 deg C near 25 deg.  What's the loss per degree at 35 deg C ? I don't have data but if I were to guess it's closer to 2%.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="solar"></category><category term="pv"></category></entry><entry><title>Inverter Topology</title><link href="/inverter-topology.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:,2013-03-31:inverter-topology.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Transformers in inverters are a must for off-grid systems because the DC side (generation and batteries) must be isolated from the AC side. Low frequency transformers are heavier but they're thought to be more efficient than high frequency ones but the situation is somewhat more complicated that that.
It's widely assumed that low frequency transformers tend to be more efficient than high frequency ones. But the situation is more subtle than that. While low frequency transformers do have higher efficiency at lower power levels which makes them suitable for low DC voltage systems, they are actually less efficient than their higher frequncy counterparts at high power levels and high voltages. The second link gives a good description of the efficiency of high and low frequency inverters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
http://www.allaboutcircuits.com/vol_2/chpt_9/8.html
http://www.homepower.com/articles/how-inverters-work
&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="inverter"></category><category term="electronics"></category></entry></feed>