<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Wattwerks</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/events.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Bellycoo PV LED Study Lamp Kit</title><link href="/bellycoo-pv-led-study-lamp-kit.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:,2014-06-15:bellycoo-pv-led-study-lamp-kit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bellycoo PV LED Study Lamp Kit&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, 30/05/14 conducted a workshop for students and teachers of rural schools around Kanakapura town to assemble their own photovoltaic led study lamps. The idea was to use available materials to create a kit that students and teachers could assemble and learn about the principles of electricity and the photovoltaic effect.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kit consists of a machined white electrical box with holes for the LEDs, 2 PCBs and a 3.7V 1150mAh Lithium ion battery. Moredetails and the manual of the kit are available &lt;a href="bellycoo.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop went surprisingly smoothly and many of the participants took to the task with more ease than we had anticipated. A couple of the teams were able to assemble their own PV modules without any breakage! Teams which found the module making too tedious were given pre-made modules to continue the process of soldering the components onto the PCBs and final assembly of the study lamp.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos of the event are available &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/76843644@N02/2mR8GZ/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. BeLLiku means 'light' in Kannada but Bellycoo is way easier in English so the name has stuck.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the popular saying goes, give a child a study lamp and she can study so long as the lamp works, teach a child to make a study lamp and she's a student for life.   &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="solar"></category><category term="pv"></category><category term="study lamp"></category></entry></feed>