<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Wattwerks</title><link href="http://tortuoise.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://tortuoise.github.io/feeds/review.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://tortuoise.github.io/</id><updated>2015-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Bescom net metering scheme</title><link href="http://tortuoise.github.io/bescom-net-metering-scheme.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:tortuoise.github.io,2015-03-26:bescom-net-metering-scheme.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Finally completed all the paperwork and got the net meter installed by Bescom for a 3KWp PV system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The initial application is easy to fill out online at this site. Though Bescom keeps changing the IP address of this. For instance here are a c&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit the local sub-division to pay the registration fee to kick off the application process. This is not a painful process if you're used to standing in queues to do simple tasks. At the Green Summit in 2015 Bescom MD Shri Pandey said this payment could be shortly made online. This still hasn't happened. Management always under-estimates the amount of work required even for seeminly simple changes. A reliable payment service is not easy to implement. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill out Format 5 with details of the equipment to be used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's wise to purchase the net meter early (well before planned installation) because  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process for testing the net meter has been changed to put the responsibility of testing on the meter vendor. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="solar"></category><category term="inverter"></category><category term="pv"></category></entry><entry><title>Powerone SGTI</title><link href="http://tortuoise.github.io/powerone-sgti.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:tortuoise.github.io,2013-12-20:powerone-sgti.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This inverter sold by Powerone in Bengaluru is imported from China where it's manufactured by &lt;a href="http://kstarpower.manufacturer.globalsources.com/si/6008803910630/pdtl/Solar-grid/1064496182/Grid-Connected-Solar-Inverter.htm"&gt;Kstar Power&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DC isolator switch and WLAN are optional so as expected the inverter arrived without either of them.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cost Rs 40k for a 3KW inverter plus 12.5% excise (excise is meant to be a manufacturing tax - it's not manufactured in India) and 5.5% KVAT on that.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installation is straight forward.&lt;br /&gt;
1. Make sure mains are off.&lt;br /&gt;
2. Test series open circuit voltage of solar array - shouldn't exceed 500VDC (rated 360VDC) but must exceed 150VDC for the MPPT to work. Connect array of solar modules to DC input ensuring correct polarity. Absolute minimum is 120VDC below which inverter turns off. Maximum short circuit current is 19A (rated 17A).&lt;br /&gt;
3. Connect AC output to mains and turn mains on.&lt;br /&gt;
4. Disconnect AC side before DC side during disconnection.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note:&lt;br /&gt;
1. The inverter comes with it's own custom connectors for the solar module array. Though these look like MC4 connectors they are not. They can be easily crimped onto some 4mm^2 or 6mm^2 wire using the clip mechanism on the connector's inside metallic part.&lt;br /&gt;
2. The inverter has a maximum continunous output current of 15A so can easily be plugged into a 15A socket.&lt;br /&gt;
3. The inverter's lcd lists the current power being output and the runnning total of the energy (in Kwh) generated.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to limited roof space and also some shading issues, connected only 6 x 250Wp Emmvee Polycrystalline modules (Voc = 37V) to get above the minimum MPPT voltage for this inverter (150V). The inverter is generating about 3A AC (~700W) at mid-day in December at 15 degrees north latitude. Not enough load available to consume all the power being generated so some of it is being lost to the grid. Need to consume more of it - time to mine some bitcoin.   &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="inverter"></category><category term="solar"></category></entry><entry><title>Vikram Eldora Solar module</title><link href="http://tortuoise.github.io/vikram-eldora-solar-module.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:tortuoise.github.io,2013-03-31:vikram-eldora-solar-module.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;36 pcs poly-crystalline solar cells, PmPP: 150Wp, VmPP:18.10V, Impp: 8.3A, Voc: 22.45V, Isc: 8.45A  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product Warranty**: 5 Years  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance Guarantee** Guaranteed Power Output of 90% for 10 Years and 80% for 25 Years  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approvals and Certificates: TUV: IEC 61215 Ed.2, IEC 61730, IEC 61701, UL1703, MCS,CEC Listed  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Module put out a maximum of 7.5A @ 19V in Bangalore in February. Perhaps the almost 1A Impp loss can be explained by the elevation of Bangalore and 30 deg heat.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one slight inconvenience about this product is that the IP-65 rated junction box has TE Connectivity connectors which aren't compatible with MC4 connectors. So if you're looking to extend your array of Vikram modules you can only do it with modules with a TE connector.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="solar"></category><category term="modules"></category></entry><entry><title>Anu Solar 600W Power Generator</title><link href="http://tortuoise.github.io/anu-solar-600w-power-generator.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Sridhar</name></author><id>tag:tortuoise.github.io,2013-03-24:anu-solar-600w-power-generator.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;600 VA Battery inverter. Anusolar sells these as solar "power generators" but what they deliver is a battery inverter and a separate PWM constant current charge controller. The inverter is loud!   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connected the inverter to one fully charged 100AH battery and it provided only about 0.4 units -a fan and a tv for a couple of hours before the battery was discharged - didn't record battery DoD. I can't imagine it's very efficient with all that energy being lost to noise - idle consumption is a massive 7W !!   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tightened the battery connections (DC connections need to be very tight to function properly) and the performance improved but not significantly. The inverter is able to invert only 0.5 - 0.6 Kwh from a fully charged 12V 100Ah battery. Either the battery is not functioning to spec or the inverter is very inefficient. The battery should be able to store 1.2Kwh (12V x 100Ah) so assuming that it discharges to 75% there should be 0.9Kwh available per cycle. But as there's only 0.6Kwh consumed by the load (a computer, modem and router) over 12 hours, the inverter is only ~70% efficient!  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="solar"></category><category term="inverter"></category></entry></feed>